foreign
[Music]
just wanted to throw out a quick shout
out to uh everybody for 300 000
subscribers which we hit about two days
ago so those watching on YouTube a very
hearty thank you it's it's a big
milestone for me it was great to see
that number and like I always say every
sub counts and it's not the biggest
chess community on YouTube
but it is an incredibly loyal uh
Community it's it's an amazing fan base
the comments are always super wholesome
and
um I could not have dreamed of a more
a more wholesome community that is more
dedicated to improving
and uh it allows me to uh to do what I
love doing and to do it without having
to
alter my kind of rules at the end of the
day I'm just a chess player I don't
think I'm ever going to play The Click
bait game or the thumbnail game as well
as some other YouTubers and I don't
begrudge them that
but at the end of the day a smaller but
more loyal Community I think is always
worth it and so the next Milestone is
going to be 400k hopefully we can do
that sometime in 2023
um
but if not that's also fine but anyways
thank you to everybody for subscribing
and supporting let's get started
so we are 1280 and this feed run is
moving faster because I didn't start by
stabilizing my rating and that was a
deliberate choice I want to spend more
time between let's say 1300 and
1700 uh it's incorporating a lot of the
feedback from chat we're playing a 1400
so a very decent player and I feel like
we've had the white pieces in like every
game this speed run but we've got white
again I'm not complaining and we are
facing E4 B6 now surprisingly we faced
this move a very healthy amount in the
speed run um I would say we faced it
over the all of the speed was maybe five
or six times and every time I've rolled
out a system that is kind of my official
recommendation against V6 it's an
incredibly effective system uh and it
really neutralizes a lot of the fun that
is associated with this offbeat opening
so we of course start with D4 just a
second
how to let some air into the building
and after Bishop B7 we start with the
simple move Knight to C3 this of course
very natural in order to defend E4 and
this is the first fork in the road so if
you don't really know anything about
playing against B6 you might be tempted
to just keep developing with Knight G1
to F3 but if you do know something about
this setup then you will know that one
of Black's main ideas is to deploy the
dark squared Bishop to before
and the point of that is not just to pin
the Knight per se it's also to apply
pressure on the E4 pawn and a lot of
white players get in trouble because
they Sleepwalk through the opening and
they end up blundering the E4 pawn and
I'll show you a couple of common
mistakes that are made against this
system after the game but the way that
you neutralize this
um is to start with a move Bishop to D3
good job Sid for pointing out this move
and after Bishop B4 who can remember and
this move is really the Crux of this
system where do we position our Knight
on G1 or do we play A3 what's the move
here
what's the move here
very good and most of you are getting it
the move is indeed 92. notice that I
didn't say Knight G2 I said 92 uh
because the other night cannot move so
technically in in notation it's it's
considered Knight E2
and of course the point of 92 should be
immediately clear we are connecting the
knights so we are taking the sting out
of the bishop capture on C3 and by
extension taking the sting out of the
bishop on B4 itself
now the move A3 is not a big mistake but
it encourages black to take the Knight
on C3 which not only ruins the pawn
structure but removes a defender of the
E4 Pawn so after A3 Bishop C3 bc3 let's
say Knight F6 the pressure on e4 becomes
rather annoying as it stands there is
well the only threat in this position
is Knight takes C4
but that's a very easy threat to defend
against and notice we don't need to play
F3 we don't need to specifically defend
the pawn again all we really need to do
is get out of the pin that's why we put
the Knight on E2 so that we don't have
to worry about Bishop takes C3 well
what's the best way to get out of the
pin we don't even need to play A3 like
literally all we have to do is literally
run away from the pin with our King we
can just Castle kingside
and in a way this is better than playing
A3 it's a little bit more flexible than
playing A3 uh because the bishop on B4
is is utterly harmless it's not it's not
affecting our position or our
development in any way and oftentimes
you actually see players taking on their
own volition and if that happens then
we've saved a Tempo on the Move A3 if
that makes sense
so notice how compact our setup is E4 is
well defended we are basically ready to
push E5 uh especially if black Castle's
King side and our Bishop is nicely
positioned aiming at the H7 Pawn so you
should already kind of begin to see the
preconditions of a king side attack and
the queen from D1 can easily drop into
H5 all we would need to do is move this
Knight out of E2 so you can kind of see
the the attack already crystallizing and
there we go Bishop takes C3 is played
that's definitely a positional Mistake
by our opponent because just giving up
the bishop pair like that is is
definitely not a good idea
um so now we've got a couple of moves on
the horizon of course E5 uh the the dark
squared Bishop can come out to G5 that
looks like a really nice Square
especially because given the absence of
the dark squared Bishop this pin is
actually very dangerous for black right
because black can't just play Bishop B4
to E7 to neutralize the pin there's no
Bishop on B4 anymore and so Bishop G5
would either Force black to make major
weaknesses on the king's side or
uh to move the queen out of out of C8
and then we would be able to capture the
Knight but all of it is a moot point our
opponent plays a good move H6 he's alert
um he's alert
and that means we need to amend our
developmental strategy a little bit now
we've got a great position and in a
great position there's often going to be
three or four ways of continuing but in
the speed run we're trying to play very
principal chess I'm trying to play
exactly the way that I would play it at
GM level and I'm trying to show you what
principled opening play actually looks
like so I'll point out two Alternatives
and then we'll go for the more
principled of the two lines the in
principle basically just means ambitious
right the main line uh so of course if
you wanted to just develop your pieces
you could do it in a variety of ways
some of you are pointing out rookie one
that's a perfectly healthy move
others are pointing out Bishop C1 to F4
or even a more modest developing move
like Bishop E3 there's nothing wrong
with that at all Bishop D2 was maybe a
little bit too passive that's a little
bit awkward if I were to move the bishop
I'd probably go to E3 thank you dirty
drop for the five Subs okay so that's
one approach right that's one bucket
another bucket is to expand our control
of the center with a move like f2f4 but
I don't really see the point of that
move because I already like how we're
controlling our Center I don't really
think we need a third Pawn in the center
now F4 you could try to push this Pawn
down to F5
and that's you know in a way kind of
similar to where we're gonna play we're
gonna play on the king's side but we're
gonna do it in a slightly more efficient
manner so that's kind of the second idea
but the line that we're gonna go for is
actually E5 we're gonna play the move E5
and this move should not make sense to
you unless you're already sensing what
our follow-up is from a positional
standpoint E5 is not a good move
and the reason it's not good
positionally is because well we're
opening up the diagonal for Black's
bishop and we're offering black a nice
Square on D5 for their Knight
all right so those are the drawbacks of
the movie five but the strength of E5 is
very specifically tied into our next
move
and the reason our next move is so
strong connects directly to Black's lack
of a dark squared Bishop right so
Black's lack of a dark squid Bishop
means that the dark squares and the the
pawns that are on dark squares are going
to be very poorly defended on the king
side combine that with Black's lack of
development on the queen side black
hasn't developed their Knight The Rook I
mean all of the pieces are kind of dead
the ones that aren't dead are clustered
on the Kings on the queen side so if we
divide the board into two segments the
king side and the queen side what's
happening on the king side all black has
there is a king and a rook that's not
mobile so what we need to do is pounce
as quickly as we can and make King side
threats and try to induce weaknesses and
the best way to do that as many of you
are indicating is indeed to drive the
queen out to G4 a very typical attacking
move across really all openings anytime
there's a weak Pawn on G7 you see this
very often in the French I would say
that most commonly you can see this move
in action in the French win hour and
that's not a coincidence because in the
win hour black plays an early Bishop
before it takes C3 so we see a very
similar kind of structure and scenario
so a couple of important remarks here
black can't Castle because we take on H6
a typical pinning Motif and white wins
on the spot
uh black and defend the G7 Pawn in a
variety of ways the move King f8 is
possible although incredibly awkward
the move that maybe some of you y'all
are thinking of here is G6 but you
should kind of visually notice that G6
creates massive weaknesses on the king
side in particular it makes this big
hole on F6 that we're going to try to
occupy with our Knight
Rook G8 also fails to a concrete tactic
as our opponent is thinking can anybody
tell me what we're gonna do against the
move to Rook to G8 and as a hint there
is a move that's actually better than
Bishop takes H6 which is possible and I
know a lot of you are thinking that but
there's an even better move
and that move is Bishop D3 to H7
we Chase The Rook away and then once the
G7 Pawn collapses the entire King side
falls apart immediately
so Rook G8 Bishop H7 if black plays G6
then of course we play Knight C3 to E4
and then we knock the Knight out of D5
with C2 C4 and we try to put our Knight
on F6
and if black plays King f8 let's try to
figure out what we're gonna do well the
moment King f8 is played you should
notice that there is the relationship
between the Rook on F1 and the King on
f8 if the f file opens in that scenario
the king is basically just toast so a
pretty automatic move against King f8 is
just to shove the pawn down to F5 which
you might say well didn't we reject this
a couple of moves ago well the situation
has changed quite a bit right the king
is now an f8 the queen is now on G4 so
the effectiveness of this has greatly
increased if I were playing Black what
I'd probably do here is actually go King
f8 and then wait for F4 and then go G6
to try to Halt the progress of the F
Pawn but that is a pretty sad product
for black obviously white is still
attacking and will cross that bridge if
we get there
it's ah they're in a relationship yeah
it's not exactly the most healthy
relationship
uh I've seen
so our opponents sinking into a deep
think and playing a fourth move which I
haven't mentioned well we kind of
mentioned this move G5 is in the same
general category as G6 I would even
argue that G5 is a more weakening move
now anytime you see a pawn like this on
G5
that pawn is actually a good thing for
white you might be annoyed by the
presence of that pawn but that pawn
could be used as kindling to kind of get
the king side fire started and normally
there are two ways of doing that if
black is already castled King side then
you might be familiar with the idea of
playing H4 in this particular scenario
what we really want to do is open up the
f file so the equivalent way of doing
that is just to play F4 which is an
excellent move in this position a move
that we actually might play but we
should also consider the alternative and
the alternative of course is Knight C3
to E4 intending uh the old idea right C4
and the Knight F6 check and that looks
uh really really uh cool as well but
actually given that our opponent played
the move G5
I don't think I can refuse F4 F4 is just
so juicy here imagine if the f file
opens up
I mean all hell is going to break loose
on the king side
but before we play F4
it's always good when you play a
committal move and F4 is a committal
move you're pushing a Pawn on the king
side it's important to kind of forecast
what could possibly go wrong what is it
that we're trying to avoid here well the
scenario that we're trying to avoid
there's only one
and that's the scenario where black
manages to escape to the queen side
right well Queen trade also but that
kind of goes without saying but if black
can quickly get their Queen side pieces
out Knight C6 Queen E7 Castle Queen side
and we've opened up the G file that
could actually backfire because you
could imagine a reality where black then
puts a rook on G8 and it combines with
the bishop on B7 to attack G2 so we
actually need to do a little bit of
calculation to ensure that that's not
going to happen let's try to concretely
look at the move F4 so after F4
black basically has to take on F4
otherwise we take on G5 and we win
so G takes F4 we can recapture with the
bishop and let's say the black tries to
quickly get uh his Knight out to C6
well in that case if you look carefully
at the king side you'll notice that
there is already a winning move and this
is a move that we talked about a little
bit earlier
and that's the queen infiltration to G7
even if it doesn't capture a pawn it's
still incredibly good because it attacks
the rook and after Rook f8 Bishop takes
H6 we're smashing through and we're
gonna trap The Rook on f8
now black can play this in a slightly
more astute way after F4 GF Bishop takes
F4 blackened start with the move Queen
to E7 and the point of starting with
Queen E7 is to meet Queen G7 with Queen
f8 this is high level defensive
technique and queen E7 is not an easy
move to play but we've got options we've
got plenty of options there after Queen
E7 we could go Knight E4 and it's very
clear to me as it should be clear to you
that I mean black is not in time to
Castle queenside there we're gonna come
up with something we're gonna have two
Tempe two entire Tempe and our pieces
are already going to be on super
dominant posts so I'm partially using my
intuition here to make this
determination but we also did some
calculations so notice how the two
combine right we calculated a little bit
to get a flavor of the position and then
I basically said okay I don't want to
spend all of my time figuring this out
because even if the worst happens in
Black Castle's Queen side it's not like
we lose the game right if you can
Envision the bishop being on F4 worst
comes to worse that Bishop can drop back
to G3 and act as a shield for a rook
that comes to G8 so even if the worst
scenario comes to fruition it's not like
White's gonna be losing we're still
going to have King side pressure we're
still going to have a Target on F7 and
it's not worth stressing about this
but I call this the worst case scenario
test and I tell students to do this they
don't do it I don't think a lot of
people do it but it's always good when
you've got a good position to ask
yourself something that sounds
pessimistic but what could possibly go
wrong right what's the worst case
scenario
and if the worst case scenario comes to
pass like how bad is it going to be and
often that gives you a good roadmap
because it immediately tells you what
your opponent is ultimately aiming for
uh and it often gives you a sense of of
what you should try to avoid which is
very important
now something I failed to mention is
that black should probably play the move
Knight D5 takes F4
which I'll be totally honest I kind of
overlooked
I don't think it's a scary move at all I
don't think it's a blunder but Knight
takes F4 might be preferable to G takes
F4
because after Knight takes F4 the one
annoying detail is that if you can
imagine Bishop takes f4g takes F4 if we
play Rook takes F4 there
what super nasty defensive move does
black have who can tell me what black
will do in that resulting position after
everything is traded on F4
Queen G5 Queen G5 and that one I missed
and queen G5 is nasty because it
pressures the G2 Pawn so it actually
forces the queen trade white is still
better in the resulting end game but we
don't want an end game we want to play
for checkmates so
again we'll cross that bridge if we get
there but that leads me to an
interesting insight
after G takes F4 I was mentioning the
move Bishop takes F4 so maybe it's
actually worth taking on D5 first in
order to prevent that and maybe I should
have even done that on the previous move
maybe F4 is a mistake and I should have
taken on D5 and then gone F4 but it's
too late now if black plays G takes F4 I
think we're gonna take on D5 with the
queen with a knight and maybe even throw
in the move Queen to G7 first
so that after Rook f8 Bishop takes F4
we're on the path to taking on H6 but I
should have done this in the other order
I should have taken on D5 first I think
and then gone F4
so this I think was a mistake by me but
it's still a pretty dominant position
it's really not uh the end of the world
but after Knight takes F4 our opponent
makes us pay the price for it
Vince Van says all that calculation
there was a deviation on move one and
that I think is a very realistic snippet
of how chess actually looks like even at
the highest level you've probably heard
the phrase long variation wrong
variation that's often attributed to
Bent Larson a legendary Danish player
and in reality that's actually how
things work right you might not want to
hear it but in my experience what often
happens is you go down these long lines
and then you actually play the move and
suddenly you discover that there is a
candidate move on the first move that
you failed to consider and then your
opponent plays it
and in chess there is that sunk cost
effect where you spend tons of time
calculating stuff that never happens but
that's also where the fun is right that
it chess wouldn't be fun if that wasn't
the case
and you should just consider it as part
of the experience and part of the fun
and in in a previous Speed Run I know
I'm I'm rambling a lot about this but I
compared it to something my English
teacher talked about which is called the
iceberg Theory uh which was formulated
by by Ernest Hemingway the author and it
basically states that I think you should
spend he said that you should spend 90
uh of the time or 90 of your character
development doesn't actually make it
into the book like you spend time
developing the character and 90 of the
personality traits and the information
about the character's life isn't
actually revealed in the book but the
process of developing the character
makes the existing 10 percent a lot
deeper and I think something similar
happens in chess where all things held
equal the more you calculate the better
it's going to be even if ten percent of
what you actually calculate appears on
the board
okay H5 H5 is another move we didn't
consider and I didn't consider it
because I just assumed that we're gonna
play Queen takes G5
and while it allows a queen Trade It
wins upon and in the resulting end game
if you look carefully after Queen G5 FG
well what do we gain from that trade
well we gain the f file
and pressure on the F7 pawn and the the
G5 pawn and let's take before I Mouse
slip the G5 Pawn can be used as a
battering ram G6 is a huge threat here
and we could still check made black in
the end game right we've got plenty of
pieces to attack with and we are still
very much playing for trackman our
opponent instantly plays D6 that's a bad
move because it totally ignores the main
threat so once again who can tell me how
we should proceed with white
and we've got actually a very
interesting alternative here in taking
on D6 and then playing Knight to B5
trying to over extend him but I cannot
refuse the move G6 just looks so juicy
open the f file and again explore
exploit Black's lack of development
while we still can
okay so G6 should make intuitives this
is the kind of move that should make
sense to you if you spent one day
playing chess right where we're just
opening up the f file we're Paving paths
for our pieces
and as a positive positional byproduct
we're also kind of ruining black
structure although that's a lot less
important than the attack the the Raging
attack we're gonna have after we
recapture
okay so if King goes to d8 we can throw
in another check on G5 you should kind
of quickly notice that if the king moves
to the seventh rank which it just did
well the tempting move is Rook to F7
check driving The Rook into the seventh
rank
and in in a classical game I would
basically play Rook F7 without too much
thought because a move like this simply
cannot be bad and that's what we're
going to do here we're just going to
give a check I'm not calculating
anything
I'm just making a move that cannot
possibly be bad
okay so well the advantages of having an
open file should be evident as this game
unfolds right this move is the product
of the file being open and you could ask
well what's the advantage of putting the
Rook on F7 well we're hunting the King
right The Rook on the seventh rank
skewers all of the important stuff that
sits on the seventh Rank and it
contributes directly to the attack
King C6 now we should start looking for
checkmate but we should also not forget
that we're simply up a pawn so a lot of
people in these kinds of positions they
actually go wrong this is a danger zone
for a lot of players as I've observed
because what tends to happen is they get
way too bogged down looking for
checkmate
forgetting that a line where let's say
you win another Pawn or you win a minor
piece is plenty sufficient in order to
win the game so we should look for
checkmate we should look for mating Nets
and mating constructions we should try
to play beautifully
but we shouldn't spend the rest of our
time getting obsessed over it and what's
interesting is that if I was playing a
bullet game and maybe this is the move
we'll end up playing in the game what
about just Knight takes D5 like the
simplest move in the position Knight
takes D5 right what's the idea well if
the king recaptures we just take another
Pawn on C7 and in that position I feel
like the king is going to get caught in
a mating net and if Knight takes D5 e
takes D5 which is more likely we just
push E6 and that pass spawn is going to
decide the game
so another simple move we could consider
is just e takes D6 opening up the
seventh rank now I like that move less
because black can play CD but that's
also plenty sufficient given that we
have six and a half minutes
we're just gonna go for it simple chess
Knight takes D5
no need to overthink it maybe the engine
would find some mating construction I
know a lot of you were attracted to the
idea of Bishop D3 because usaba should
be five mate
but Black's not gonna cooperate Bishop
D3 Knight takes C3
we play BC and then we have like a four
Bishop E5 and I saw all of that but it's
a little bit too speculative and it's
not worth it
and we might still be able to Checkmate
the black king nothing okay King D5
played I'm a little surprised
well we I think continue grabbing
I don't see any compelling reason not to
take on C7 with Tempo with Tempo we
attack the bishop and now we have a
second extra pawn and these are the best
kinds of attacks your op two pawns and
you're attacking so there's nothing
really at stake here
Bishop A6 all right now
again let's try to play Simple chess
and in the spirit of simple chess there
is yet another move that I see
immediately which is the simplest move
on the board and it requires the least
amount of calculation what am I talking
about here it's not C4 it's not B3 all
of that requires calculation because it
might not be Checkmate it's simpler than
that just e takes D6
just e takes D6 right it's you start
with a capture that's what you're
supposed to do I'm just following the
rules so why is he takes D6 so good
well black is forced to recapture with
the King that should make sense to you
otherwise we have a third extra pawn and
it sits on D6 after e d King takes D6
the key is to see the follow-up move and
if you see the follow-up move then it
should immediately make sense why I'm so
attracted to this option and it's Bishop
to F4 check basically leading to
Checkmate and also defending the Rook
with the bishop so we're just going for
it Ed
now Rook have fate would be a funny move
here it would threaten made on F1
so you should always always always keep
an eye on things like that right if
black plays Rook f8 here I know a lot of
players would just kind of quickly play
D7 but again it's the worst case
scenario test the reason I'm aware of
this is because we haven't yet developed
our Queen side and anytime that's the
case you should be on the lookout for
various ways to punish that
so Marion District asks are there
suggested Rules of Order to look at
moves well checks and captures right you
start with checks and captures so I did
briefly consider the move C4 check which
some of you suggested but I didn't
understand it because Bishop takes C4
and and we're at a dead end
then you look at captures right then you
look at Ed so I was literally just
following the rules that's all I was
doing and we get get the bishop out with
Tempo and the rest should be a cleanup
task
so my instinct in this position is to
bring the last piece into the game Rook
to E1 but if we look a little bit more
carefully we might discover a mating net
um let me think for a second here I do
want to do something pretty
and I have an idea I'm trying to see if
it works it's a really pretty mating
construction and I think it works oh
this will be really cute if this works
yeah this will be really cute if it
works now there's multiple mating
constructions right rookie one is plus a
thousand because Bishop comes back to E4
and I'm violating the rules of my own
speed run here in trying to play for
beauty rather than playing for
efficiency
uh and black has a way of okay but we're
gonna start with Bishop to E5 this is
the start of the mating net
and what is the point of this move well
the point of this move is just to defend
the D4 Pawn with Tempo now the king is
out of Escape squares and anytime the
king is out of squares just by
definition you start looking for
checkmate you start looking for mating
constructions Target positions and I see
two mating constructions here from
either side rookie1 and Bishop to E4 is
a mate but the pretty mate is B3 and C4
mating with a pawn notice that after B3
black and play the move B5 to prevent C4
but anytime a pawn is pushed you ask
yourself what squares are weakened as a
result and you should quickly see that
the C5 Square becomes accessible to
blackstroke as another Checkmate okay
now there's a really pretty detail if
black plays the move Rook h8 to C8
and all of this you might say you might
be rolling your eyes at this and saying
well we're totally winning like anything
wins here why am I spending so long you
know being pedantic about this and again
it's because this is where you develop
skills right it's the low stakes
positions where you can really drill
down and figure stuff out now my
opponent played what I hoped you would
play because here we have a really
pretty idea
don't try this at home
but what should we now try well we
should consider our two mating moves and
actually both of them end up working
let's start with the move B3
B3 thread and C4 what is our opponent's
idea our opponent's idea is to take the
bishop on G6 thereby opening up an
escape path for the king through E4
so B3 looks like a terrible blunder but
let's extend our calculation by just one
move B3 Rook takes G6 white to play
there is a slow quiet and absolutely
deadly move in that position and black
death just found it B3 Rook takes G6 and
Rook to E1 depriving the king of the
last Escape square and threatening C4
and in that position it's still not over
black can deploy the Knight to C6 in
order to intercept the rook's connection
to C4 but in that position we have
another Checkmate in one and again it
stems from the fact that when a piece
moves out and black has so many squares
to keep track of there's going to be new
mating constructions based on what black
did and all of you are seeing it this is
awesome the move is Rook to D7 Checkmate
in that position let's go for it we play
B3 and yes we could also start from the
other end we could also start with
rookie one this is a symmetrical
construction rookie one Rook takes G6 B3
would also work
I wouldn't necessarily recommend this to
you in a real game because the stakes
suddenly get high if this doesn't work
all of a sudden we're down a piece and
you know you risk messing this up
so a totally viable continuation would
be of course to play rookie one in this
position but it would also be to play a
move like I don't even a bishop well
Bishop D3 is probably bad like Bishop F7
here would be simple and there would be
nothing wrong with it maybe even Bishop
to H7 to keep control over the E4 Square
but this is the clinical method this is
the clinical way and let's see if our
opponent even sees Rook takes G6 which
is not a given
why is Bishop D3 bad because if you
notice after Bishop D3 and the trade our
pawns lose their Mobility our pawns lose
their Mobility we lose the possibility
of playing C4 yes our opponent goes for
it and the king is suddenly quite safe
on D5 in that resulting position of
course still completely winning and
there's actually a very cute mating
construction that we could try to build
using Bishop D3 but
um it's it's not the efficient way
yeah Seth that's exactly what I was
thinking but I thought Knight A6 there
and black black might be able to survive
so a technique that I recommend to
people if you have time for it and
you're trying to test whether a certain
construction actually leads to Checkmate
this is especially good if it involves a
sacrifice on your end and if the stakes
are high right if you're really trying
to ensure whether something works what
you can do is actually put on your
computerized and literally look at every
single legal move from your opponent and
that takes a lot less time than you
would think because you can go piece by
piece you could take the queen then take
the Rooks then take the Bishops Knights
pawns and there aren't actually that
many legal moves available in a position
so you do that in order to ensure that
you're not missing a hidden defense in a
given position let's do that here okay
The Rook cannot move on a the Rokon G6
has only one move that avoids Checkmate
that's Rook takes G2 and that obviously
doesn't work the bishop B5 C4 B7 C8 all
of that doesn't
defend Bishop D3 we still play C4 Bishop
E2 well that is a defense but we play
Rook take C2
Bishop F1 we play C4 okay Knight Knight
Knight D7 we play C4 Knight C6 we
already discussed Rook to D7 is mate
pawn moves H4 doesn't help B5 didn't
help because of C4 that's literally it
that was it the King has no moves
so in many cases actually looking at
every legal move is a good way of
checking for these freak defenses
um and we have checkmated our opponent
in 23 moves but a very rich game a lot
happened in those 23 moves so a lot to
talk about in our analysis
let me pull up the game
all right so we've had this particular
line already quite a few times Bishop to
D3 and I won't necessarily delve into
all of the details again
but since this is the opening speed run
we're going to do a little bit of
opening analysis here
so in this position the interesting
thing is that Bishop before I believe is
a serious mistake well not a mistake
it's a big inaccuracy and after Knight
E2 it's already like plus one according
to the engine
and and this is why Bishop D3 is such a
tricky move because when you're taught
this line from the black side you're
taught that Bishop B4 is the natural
follow-up to almost everything that
white does
so we have a couple of questions here uh
first of all klumar is asking why not A3
and A3 is one of White's best moves
there are many ways to get an advantage
against one B6 the reason I don't like
this move as much is because it's not
very efficient and after Knight F6 I
didn't find anything overly convincing
for white when I analyzed
uh for I think the line goes E5 Knight
to D5 and you got kind of a weird alakai
into here
uh but in any case I wasn't totally
convinced uh by this line for a way of
course it's also an advantage
so after Bishop D3
the best move for black is probably to
play Knight F6 actually to to switch
gears and to start by developing the
Knight
and here you still play the move Knight
G2 E2 so this is a compact setup that
works no matter where black puts their
pieces
and I want to show you all a very
important line
so oftentimes black can play this like a
French black plays the move D5 and
naturally you respond to the five at
which point there are two viable
retreating moves the first is to move
the Knight back to D7
now who can tell me why white has to be
very careful in this position what is
Black's threat and I don't use the word
threat lightly this is a serious threat
and if white ignores it white could end
up being worse very quickly yeah the
move is C5 now you might say well C5
isn't dangerous in other openings well
that's because you have the possibility
of defending the pawn chain with C3 here
you don't so things could go downhill
quickly for instance after C5 if you
play the move F4 you lose your Bishop to
C4 and I've seen people blunder like
this now funnily enough white is still
better here after F5 I can sack the
bishop but it's not worth going for it
because white is a much better move the
move here is Knight F4
and if black persists with C5 there is a
beautiful tactical shot that wins the
game on the spot that's why this is such
a dangerous line let's see if anybody
can find this idea it exists in
different openings
okay very good knight takes C6 is
correct knife E6 forcing the pawn off
and now the queen drives into H5 and the
game is over because if G6 then of
course of course Bishop G6
takes takes King E7 and white wins every
one of black species after Bishop G5
if black plays the immediate King E7
which is relatively speaking more
resilient then there is yet another
beautiful idea Bishop G5 check forces
Knight F6
efgf and now the coup de gras Bishop
takes F6 King takes F6 in a beautiful
retreating skewer now it's very
important that at the end of this line
the bishop has no way of moving away
with Chuck I have made this point before
you always have to check for this if a
line ends in this kind of scenario right
if White's King was on D2 black would be
winning after Bishop H6 here there is no
Discovery what is up a queen so the line
works out beautifully
and after Knight F4 black is already in
very big trouble the engine move here is
this weird move G6 but it's not weird if
you understand the idea it defends the
H5 Square
but still it's plus minus after Queen G4
white unrolls a big attack on the king
side
again C5 Knight takes C6 and Bishop G6
wins so black has to play the super
awkward move Queen to E7
and now according to my analysis the
simple Queen back to G3 is very very
strong you just solidify your position
and if black plays C5
the Knight jumps into B5 of another
typical idea and I mean black just
totally collapses on the dark squares
this is already plus five so you can
analyze this further on your own but uh
Knight fd7 Knight F4 is very bad for
black now the second move involves yet
another very pretty idea and that is
Knight E4 this is considered the sort of
more ambitious line
and here there is another very pretty
line
so there is a variation of the Karo Khan
there is a variation of the Karo Khan
where um let me see if I can remember
the two nights Caro black plays Knight
F6 white plays E5 and black plays Knight
E4 it's a similar concept does anybody
know there there's a weird move that
white is supposed to play here one of
the main moves does anybody know what
I'm talking about
all I'll say is that it's a weird move
Vince Vance is familiar with the theory
and the move is Knight c3d2
so there's a concept that involves
moving the Knight away and that night
was an escape hatch for black right D3
Knight takes C3 was the idea now you're
threatening to play D3 and push the
Knight out of the center
now black of course has the move Queen
B6 threatening Checkmate but then white
plays D4 and the line goes on but the
basic concept is that you move the
Knight away and play D3 this is a
concept which also exists in the closed
Sicilian in a completely different
scenario
so I'll make a couple of sample moves
here to show you in the close Sicilian
an idea that was taught to me many years
ago
so let's play uh you know one of the
main lines whatever castles castles
so this is purely hypothetical I will
asterisk this by saying that this isn't
necessarily good in the position I'm
showing it to you but it's a general
idea so in this position whites
um ultimate idea is to remove the knight
from D4 but you don't want to do it
while giving away the dark squid Bishop
so you come up with the idea of moving
the Knight away and playing C3
now sometimes white can even move the
other night away to prevent the escape
hatch with Knight takes C2 and then play
Knight T1 and then play C3 and I can
probably find you some games where this
happens
um in a close to selling in fact I'm
going to do just that I'm going to make
a quick search and see if I can find any
examples of the actual this actually
happening so I prove to you that this is
not
a load of BS
but of course as I'm doing this you
should already be thinking about where
I'm going with this in the context of
the current game it's okay so this game
Klinger is as strong I am and in this
position watch what he does
he plays close to silly and he plays
Knight D1
E6 and Knight C1 and after B4 he plays
the move C3 chasing the Knight away and
then he gets his Knights back into
civilization with Knight E2 and he's
deprived the C6 Knight of an important
Square now probably
white should have considered starting
with Knight C1 because after Knight C1
he gives black a chance to trade the
knights but I guess he wasn't too
worried about that
so in any case this is another similar
idea
now we finally transition to the
position at hand that we're analyzing
and that is okay in the Karo Khan we
talked about this
and right now we're talking about Knight
F6 92 D5 E5 and Knight E4 having this
knowledge who can tell me what the top
move is for white
try to apply the knowledge why did I
show you the previous examples what's
the equivalent in this position
and this is amazing you guys are getting
it fantastic Knight B1 and see when you
understand the idea the move stops
looking so outlandish it also contains
the nice byproduct that you can now push
the C Pawn so if black but the main idea
is of course to play F3 and actually
trap the Knight on e4
if black plays a random move F3 wins the
game
Knight G5 and H4 traps the Knight on G5
and black has to give the Knight away
and if black plays C5 trying to
counteract with C4 then white doesn't
need to hurry with F3 white can start
with C3 so that C4 is not dangerous
and then if black plays Bishop E7 now
again F3 wins the Knight black is in
trouble here according to the engine
black has to play very concretely to
avoid his Knight getting trapped but
black has to go take Stakes Bishop B4
check but that gives the B1 Knight a
nice developing Square on C3 and just
look at how nice this position looks
Queen G4 is going to be your next move
and White's got everything on perfect
squares the bishop looks dumb it's plus
over minus and all you really need to
remember is the move Knight B1 get
impress some people at a cocktail party
with it
so that folks is how you meet Knight F6
now we get to the game continuation
which is a lot easier to understand here
we just play very straightforward moves
um and I believe that this almost busts
the line I mean I mean why is this much
better everywhere in this line
so after 92 Knight F6 castles King side
plus over minus means that white has a
clear advantage
so in this position black of course
should probably just Castle I mean
taking on their own volition is a recipe
for disaster as we saw but even after
black castles we can play a bunch of
different moves we can play Bishop G5
but I quite like the move um I quite
like the move E5
which is the idea that I pointed out
during the game and if black plays
Knight T5 then the game is already over
Knight D5 Bishop D5 and who can remind
me of White's main attacking idea in
this position if you're watching on
YouTube pause and try to figure out the
next move it's a very important move
and it's a natural move but nonetheless
you have to remember this concept if
you're developing your knight to E2
so some of you might be thinking oh it's
F4 F5 but that's slow and cumbersome the
move is actually Knight to F4 and the
eval is like plus five
so let's say black moves the bishop back
to B7 just look at Black's King Black's
King is wide open and now you go Knight
to H5 another important idea and not
necessarily a natural move I think a lot
of people are attracted to Queen H5
which keeps a big Advantage which keeps
a big Advantage but if you do this
thinking oh I'm so smart I'm going to go
Knight H5 on the next move black is in
time to play rookie eight
and if you play Knight H5 black somehow
defends with Bishop effeda Houdini act
and if you go Knight F6 check of course
Queen takes F6 EF and black somehow gets
the game into an end game so the way to
do this is actually to go Knight H5 and
then Queen to G4 and put the Knight on
F6 which is an idea that paralleled
something that we were discussing during
the game
so if if black tries to do the same
thing here and go rookie eight
other than Queen she4 which wins on the
spot we can play Knight takes G7 but
this is much simpler bishop f8 and even
better the Knight F6 check is actually
Knight takes G7 Bishop G7 Bishop H6 with
Checkmate imminence on G7
again it's not like after castles black
is okay black is not okay but if black
plays the accurate move Knight to E8
then this is I think the way to minimize
White's Advantage white can still play
Knight F4 and this is still very
dangerous but the Knight on E8 is an
important defensive piece after black
plays Bishop C3 Knight C3 I honestly
feel like this is already borderline
losing for black it's just so so nice
for white
so
okay our opponent plays H6 which I think
is maybe the Lesser evil and now we
respond by keeping our foot on the gas
pedal E5 and queen G4 hopefully I did a
good job of explaining the logic behind
this idea during the game so I won't
repeat myself
um but after
um just a moment folks
yeah so
this is really interesting I'm I'm
looking up something with the engine
here
just to make sure that I have the
accurate understanding
yeah this is very very cool actually
so I discovered something interesting
and what that is that F4 is actually the
correct move so we play Queen G4
to quickly reiterate why this move is so
strong well it's strong because the pawn
on G7 is so weak and Black's King side
is so undeveloped right and it just a
Barren and empty so if G6 then during
the game I was pointing out 94 followed
by C4 and Knight F6 this doesn't even
deserve further analysis this is
overwhelming
if castles then of course Bishop takes
H6 G6 and Bishop takes G6 with mate
so G5 is actually a sensible move from
that perspective and we could have still
played 94 but F4 is in fact the best
move and here's the fascinating thing
Knight takes F4 is what I pointed out as
a potentially scary a potentially scary
move
let me remind you that after G takes F4
the winning line is to play Knight takes
D5 and then to play Queen G7 and then to
play Bishop takes F4 and black simply
cannot stop Bishop takes H6 and queen f8
check at a minimum and that's just the
simplest
so
that wins the game now after Knight F4
there's a beautiful sequence I saw this
move I was aware of its existence but I
didn't realize how strong it was until I
just checked with with the computer
um well I'll let people have a stab at
it white to play and win in this
position and it's it's largely a forcing
line but it's a relatively long line
yeah rucksack Rook takes effort but why
why Rook takes F4 what's the point of
sacking when you can do the same thing
with Bishop takes F4 well the only point
is to preserve the dark squirt Bishop
well what do we know about the dark
squared Bishop in this position what's
the Key Construction well we already
know what the ideal construction is here
from the other lines and that's to start
with Queen G7
forcing Ro Cafe the notice that Queen G5
doesn't work because this is a check
otherwise they'd be made and otherwise
Queen Q5 would work but after a workout
f8 Bishop F4 black simply cannot stop
Bishop takes H6 with a battery Against
The Rook now it's not the end of the
line black will deploy the queen to E7
will take on H6 and black will go Knight
C6 and a lot of newer players here as
well as a lot of experienced players
would just say okay I have to take on f8
and I have to get this end game
something like Bishop E4 and of course
it's it should be a technical win for
white white is up a pawn but there's
plenty of fight left
but there's this engine move here that's
that's so strong and it and it's the
drop back to G5 it sounds
counter-intuitive but really it's not
you have to prevent black from castling
right that's that's the threat is to
cast the queen side Bishop G5 shifts the
bishop and prevents it black has to play
Queen before
and what do we do now well now we can
employ an idea from a little bit earlier
we've got several winning lines one of
them is to play Knight to B5 which I
know some of you are thinking about and
then to play A3
and then to make a deceptively simple
move in this position just freaking Rook
F1 and Rook takes F7 is going to be the
mating idea I mean let's just just look
at this or Bishop G6 I mean we're just
gonna put something on an aggressive
square and it's gonna be made
but as I indicated the best move is
probably to play Knight to E4 and Knight
F6 with a totally devastating discovered
attack following up okay black can take
one Pawn with Chuck big whoop King H1
and for example if Queen takes the five
Knight F6 King E7 the simplest move is
Knight back to G4 winning the queen on
the Spy winning the game on the spot
so either option leads to Victory but
the key move in all of this is Bishop
back to G5 hopefully this line made
sense and if if I went too fast you can
always replay the line on your own board
you can look at it with an engine on
your own but ultimately it is pretty
forced so it should make sense to you
notice that after Queen G7 King E7
doesn't work because of this well-timed
check driving the king back and then we
take the Rook what if F6 asks some of
you great question
so the question goes what if F6 I assume
you mean in this position what if F6
well here we can go Bishop G6 check
King T8 and now the best move is e takes
F6 right easy to miss move
but don't roll out options that trade
quick I mean technically it's a queen
trade but White's just about to get
another queen with mate
so definitely not a super not like a
very computer-ish line but nonetheless a
line that involves having to find a
bunch of accurate moves
okay
so hopefully that answers the questions
H5 from that perspective might actually
be the best that black can do here and
that is saying a great deal and this end
game is totally lost now maybe Black's
Last Chance was to play the proactive
move Knight to B4 black must prevent G6
at all costs if G6 comes you saw how
quickly black crumbles so maybe night
before gives some chances but we could
still play G6 and after Knight D3 we
have the Intermezzo gf7 and the engine
the engine believes that Black's best
chances are to be found after Rook to H7
black will win black will win the pawn
back
but white can stick a rook on F6
beautiful square and slide it over to G6
with Bishop H6 check to follow and the
attack is Raging this is around plus
three so obviously not exactly a saving
line
um yeah the line is findable in a
rapidly even in a Blitz game but our
opponent goes D6 trying to break up the
center and of course G6 yeah it's
vicenzook is an alternative word for
intermed so that's the German term
um but but G6 is is totally and utterly
destructive and we don't really need to
talk much about the rest of the game but
uh there are a couple of nice lines that
I can showcase so here the position
really plays itself and the final
mistake was King C6 I mean the King on
C6 is is uh just total toast I think the
last way to keep you know the the the
game going would have been to play King
C8 and here again I think the simplest
is just e takes D6 C takes D6 and who
can tell me a nice clinical move in this
position that creates insurmountable
pressure against Black's weaknesses
what's the what's the surgical way to
win this yeah Knight B5 or alternatively
we've been preferring Knight E4
cing rook d8 and now c4 same idea as
before
and after the Knight moves away from D5
we can deploy the bishop to F4
increasing the pressure on D6 and if we
can force Bishop takes E4 then look at
White's Bishops and look at what they're
aiming at D5 Rook C7 is just mate just
brutal and after Knight 8 C6 we can just
play A3 disattaching the knights from
each other and winning the game
this is all very very straightforward
chess but after King C6 Knight takes D5
it's all over as well after e takes D5 I
was planning to play ed6
C takes C6 and now what you should
notice is that the Rook makes contact
with the bishop so a nice idea would be
to to distract the king and you could
say oh I see it the move is B4 and B4 is
good but black can prevent it with B5
what's a more Artful way and a more
Unstoppable way to achieve what B4
achieves it's actually to play C for yes
very good you guys are sharp and after
DC not Bishop E4 check because of D5 but
the immediate D5 drives the king out and
wins the bishop on B7 and wins the game
okay so C4 is a pretty standard idea
that you should remember
okay in the game our opponent plays uh
King takes D5 we we take another pawn
and here we basically find The Mating
mechanism he takes D6 winning another
Pawn
deploying the bishop to F4 and finding
the mating mechanism now according to
the engine rookie one is the fastest
mate which would totally understand we
played Bishop E5 and the reason this is
technically not immediate mate is
because black can play the pathetic move
Knight C4 Knight C6
of course we can just take on h8 and
it's over
uh but and after Rook age the funny
thing is we win the bishop as well with
check and check so it's not like black
keeps any pieces alive
but uh okay our opponent plays Rook H6
and now of course B3 is the pretty
pretty mate
and should black stall to get to the
boxing here yes exactly and after Rook
G6 rookie won it's all over B5 Rook C5
this is important this is important and
Knight C6 Rook D7 has happened in the
game is also important
um otherwise against any other movie
plays C4 and then BC except Bishop B2
which case we take now I wanted to point
out a funny detail which is that some of
you were proposing Bishop D3 and I was
trying to mention why this is not such a
good idea the funny thing is that white
has a mating construction here that
works only because the pawn is on D3 and
what mating construction is that well
it's to play Rook C1 and then Rook to C5
mate
so it's a very pretty idea
but this would be a good example of Hope
Chest right you're not you're this is
slow and black can beat white to the
punch with the move Knight to A6
attacking The Rook now with the Rook on
C1 Rook D7 would be made now Rook D7 is
not made because the king escapes so
here you have to basically start not
from scratch you're still completely
winning but it's totally unnecessary
B3 is is the clinical way to do it and
if you
and if you as I said you can play Bishop
H7 or you can play Bishop F7 uh but but
you shouldn't go for these lines unless
you've calculated them out completely
and you're going to make some mistakes
right you're going to be winning and
sometimes you're gonna go for mate and
it's normal once in a blue moon to to
forget about a defense right you can't
be perfect but all things held equal
this Cutthroat type of Chess is still
the best way to convert winning
positions
and after Knight C6 Rick D7 the game
ends and we Checkmate the black king in
the center
and that folks concludes our analysis
this was a nice game it was a short game
it's a simple game but it was a game
that showcased first of all the power of
the system I think against B6 which you
will face and second of all the the
immense power of this idea E5 Queen G4
right when when the king side is
abandoned like this uh putting a queen
on G4 is super effective and then using
our Pawn as a hook right in order to
open up our opponent's Pawn is a hook in
order to open up files and then uh just
simple chess blasting the file open and
then searching for a mating net in the
end and uh that that was all it took all
right well I will lastly point out that
there is more Theory here there's Knight
F6 in this position which uh definitely
should be should be talked about
although after Bishop to D3
most of the time Black Goes E6 sometimes
Black Goes D6 and Knight bd7 this also
exists but I'm sure we'll get another
chance to talk more deeply about Theory
remember I'm trying to introduce the
theory to you in bite-sized portions
rather than just you know loading you up
with a big file and just a bunch of
boring lines hopefully it's it's more
manageable that way and this will be out
on YouTube very shortly well thank you
everybody for watching and thanks again
for watching the speed run bye
[Music]
thank you